<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Hexo</title>
  
  
  <link href="https://www.cz5h.com/words/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://www.cz5h.com/words/"/>
  <updated>2021-02-07T15:25:52.900Z</updated>
  <id>https://www.cz5h.com/words/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>长征部落格</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="https://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Cut off the tail [redundant parts]</title>
    <link href="https://www.cz5h.com/words/9731.html"/>
    <id>https://www.cz5h.com/words/9731.html</id>
    <published>2021-02-06T23:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-02-07T15:25:52.900Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<html><head></head><body><p>This is a training for shorten your words. Writing craps could help us make enough words in a short time. But now we need to focus inside: cut off the sentences or descriptions that are not related to your writing objects. Training this with three phrases: write 300 words to describe one thing, then shorten it to 200 words, and finally 100 words. Compare these three versions you can find the strange parts in your words.</p><a id="more"></a><h3 id="Phrase-A-300-words"><a href="#Phrase-A-300-words" class="headerlink" title="Phrase A - 300 words"></a><strong>Phrase A - 300 words</strong></h3><p>In order to compute the similarity between the low dimensional projections and high dimensional source datasets, we create a way to connect them. Since we know that the process of dimensionality reduction is like a black box, so it is hard to find out the match point of the source dataset in projections. Thus we used an inverse way to build the matching.</p><p>In 2D projections, we can combine the pixels information with every point. Then, for each point, we can find the matching point or items in the source dataset. Because we have all information with the source data, we can achieve this by programming. After doing that, we connected the points in low and high dimensions. Next, what we did is to compute similarity. Based on the same idea, we still focus on the low dimensional projection. We select one point/pixel, and compute a circle area around this point When we get the neighborhoods, we find all of their matching points. Finally, we used Euclidean distance to compute these two sets of points.</p><p>Besides, considering the process of computing are almost same as the variance computing, so we also create methods based on variance. Now, we have built a new brilliant mechanism to compute similarity. The next step is to test the way to compute distance.</p><p>We choose more than 10 datasets and made a set of experiments for the case study later. After getting our explanations, we tried to explain what our explanations showed. From our test, we found a suitable range for parameters for most cases we tested. </p><h3 id="Phrase-B-200-words"><a href="#Phrase-B-200-words" class="headerlink" title="Phrase B - 200 words"></a><strong>Phrase B - 200 words</strong></h3><p>We create a way to compute the similarity between the low dimensional projections and high dimensional source datasets. Because the process of dimensionality reduction is like a black box, so we used an inverse way to build the matching.</p><p>Because we have all information with the source data, we can find the matching point or items in the source dataset. After doing that, we connected the points in low and high dimensions. Next, we compute similarity. based on the same idea. We select one point/pixel, and compute a circle area around this point When we get the neighborhoods, we find all of their matching points. Finally, we used Euclidean distance to compute these two sets of points.</p><p>Besides, considering the process of computing is similar with the variance computing, so we also create methods based on variance. Now, we have finished the way to compute similarity. </p><p>We choose more than 10 datasets and made a set of experiments for the case study later. After getting our explanations, we tried to explain what our explanations showed. From our test, we found a suitable range for parameters for most cases we tested. </p><h3 id="Phrase-C-100-words"><a href="#Phrase-C-100-words" class="headerlink" title="Phrase C - 100 words"></a><strong>Phrase C - 100 words</strong></h3><p>We create a way to compute the similarity between the low dimensional projections and high dimensional source datasets. We used an inverse way to build the matching.</p><p>Because we have all information with the source data, we can find the matching point or items in the source dataset. We select one point/pixel, and compute a circle area around this point when we get the neighborhoods, we find all of their matching points. Finally, we used Euclidean distance to compute these two sets of points.</p><p>Besides, we also create methods based on variance. We choose more than 10 datasets for the case study later. After getting our explanations, we tried to explain what our explanations showed. From our test, we found a suitable range for parameters for most cases we tested. </p></body></html>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;html&gt;&lt;head&gt;&lt;/head&gt;&lt;body&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a training for shorten your words. Writing craps could help us make enough words in a short time. But now we need to focus inside: cut off the sentences or descriptions that are not related to your writing objects. Training this with three phrases: write 300 words to describe one thing, then shorten it to 200 words, and finally 100 words. Compare these three versions you can find the strange parts in your words.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="English" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/categories/English/"/>
    
    
    <category term="training" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/training/"/>
    
    <category term="description" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/description/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Describe one thing in 10 minutes</title>
    <link href="https://www.cz5h.com/words/1489.html"/>
    <id>https://www.cz5h.com/words/1489.html</id>
    <published>2021-02-04T23:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-02-07T15:25:52.900Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<html><head></head><body><p>If you want to speed up your writing, then you can try this training. Find a quiet place and select some words or objects you want to describe. It’s better to describe some scientific objects since we are training our scientific writing. Think about a word, and just write words, you can write craps but do not change it when you’re writing. Just keep writing until you think you can stop (about 300 words), then you can review what you’ve made, and modify it to the final version.</p><a id="more"></a><h3 id="Visualization"><a href="#Visualization" class="headerlink" title="Visualization"></a><strong>Visualization</strong></h3><p>Visualization is a very scientific word, which could be seen in lots of papers and involved in almost every research area. The basic idea is to create images or visible objects to represent the numbers or text of the resource data. It is a kind of natural thinking that transfers the information into visual signals. Scientists have found that almost all information we get come from our vision, which means images, animes, or other types of visual objects are the fast way for humans to get information. In detail, the common visual signals include color, size, luminance, texture, etc. With these signals, we can deal with most vision problems. But the new challenge is how to handle the data that include hundreds even thousands of dimensions.</p><p>Using statistical methods, researchers have created many algorithms to select the special dimensions from data, they can get lots of meaningful results with these methods, but unfortunately, they are all numbers or text, so these unreadable results lead this problem into the visualization field, which could perfectly return understandable results. From here, visualization became more and more important in the data analysis field, especially multidimensional data analysis. Nowadays it has become an independent research area and will continue to play a big role in every research field. </p><h3 id="Image-based-method"><a href="#Image-based-method" class="headerlink" title="Image-based method"></a><strong>Image-based method</strong></h3><p>When dealing with the dimensional data, images always used to represent the final project result. It could show some information like clusters, density, or overlappings. But that’s all comes from the image itself, we can’t get any information from the original data once we get the final image. If we want to build a mapping between them, like using an area in an image to finding the matching points in resource data. The traditional methods usually need to create a structure to store all point location, which is very complex and only support a small number of points. </p><p>In this kind of case, Image-based methods could have a good performance. For most scatterplots, the images are generated by the real result of algorithms, the key point is that there is a connection for every point between numbers and images. We can use this kind of connection to solve the above question. With the pixels computing, it could execute with a fast speed and don’t need much middle control since it runs the same operations for each point.</p><h3 id="Web-application"><a href="#Web-application" class="headerlink" title="Web application"></a><strong>Web application</strong></h3><p>(not about research, just something different)</p><p>Nowadays, web applications have become a very important part of our daily life. What is the web application, compared with traditional applications, it should not contains heavy back-end components, and should easy enough to build and deploy. Specifically, they usually programmed by pure front-end languages like Javascript/Html/CSS or introduce the support of back-end with Nodejs, Vue, or React. </p><p>For the most front-end developer, build a complex environment is always the boring and annoying part when they want to write and publish something. Find an easy way to do that is a common idea for every one of them. Now some public service producer like Github and Vercel has supported the hosting service that allows users to deploy their static resources on the servers. This is a big step, which means without building any servers by themself, and publish their content on the Internet. </p><p>Now, not only the programmer,  but also lots of students, bloggers, or companies start to use this service to show their content on this freeway. Unfortunately, there is no service to support the back-end for Github or Vercel. At the same time, Glitch appeared and brought a brand new service, which allows users to create applications with Nodejs. Besides, they also have an online coding system that could edit and publish with the browser. When users create an application, Glitch will start a docker service. With this kind of virtual technique,  they could support building thousands of applications every day. This is a really amazing service, that could let a big group of people program a more complex project without any local environment.  </p></body></html>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;html&gt;&lt;head&gt;&lt;/head&gt;&lt;body&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you want to speed up your writing, then you can try this training. Find a quiet place and select some words or objects you want to describe. It’s better to describe some scientific objects since we are training our scientific writing. Think about a word, and just write words, you can write craps but do not change it when you’re writing. Just keep writing until you think you can stop (about 300 words), then you can review what you’ve made, and modify it to the final version.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="English" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/categories/English/"/>
    
    
    <category term="training" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/training/"/>
    
    <category term="description" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/description/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>为什么开启这个里世界？</title>
    <link href="https://www.cz5h.com/words/cd67.html"/>
    <id>https://www.cz5h.com/words/cd67.html</id>
    <published>2021-01-31T23:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-02-07T16:40:53.207Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<html><head></head><body><p>很久没有静下心来写东西了，总是沉迷于搞些小玩意儿，比如小插件、小工具，主站的主题越来越复杂强大，这也算是我一天天看着成长起来的，然而我却掉队了，依然徘徊在2.0版本，没什么理由，只是觉得自己喜欢修修补补，今天搞个特效，明天加个功能，很有趣我也很入迷。但最近越来越觉得，我正在远离创作者的阵营，离“开发者”又相距甚远，所以为了纠正下状态，我唯一能做且想做的，就是找回书写的乐趣，更进一步讲，是找回不断总结的习惯。为此，我翻了一堆主题，力图寻找到一个专注写作专注文字的主题，很幸运，icarus的主题作者的另一主题minos，完美的迎合了我的口味，简洁但绝非简单，扩展比较全面。因此就有这个页面啦。今后的日子里，我会在这里放英语文章、中文随想或者是非技术类的文字向文章，欢迎多多支持！</p><a id="more"></a><h3 id="需要做的事"><a href="#需要做的事" class="headerlink" title="需要做的事"></a><strong>需要做的事</strong></h3><ul><li>配置项补全，但我不想配置单独的分类页标签页了，这样就非常棒了，依附于主站，没有多余的内容嵌套。</li><li>评论，这是得需要的，打算仍然用valine，配合页面计数，直接一步到位了。</li><li>页面访问统计，这个应该跟随主站，所以统计代码直接迁移即可。</li><li>添加返回主站的操作入口，比如按钮，还没想好。</li><li>SEO，这部分不重要吧，已经是很主观的东西了。</li><li>换一下头图。</li></ul><!--### **构建步骤**- 主项目(Volantis) hexo clean && hexo g ——> public(default)- 副项目(Minos) 修改root:minos/ public:minos/- 副项目(Minos) hexo clean && hexo g ——> public/minos- 移动 move public/minos public- 主项目(Volantis) hexo deploy 完成提交文件结构- mianHexo  - source    - _post  - theme    - volantis  - generate.bat- subHexo  - source    - _post  - theme    - minos- allinone.bat@call hexo clean >nul 2>nul@call hexo g >nul 2>nulecho Main theme rendered ...cd ../Volantis-minos@call hexo clean >nul 2>nul@call hexo g >nul 2>nulecho Sub theme rendered ...cd ../puremove ../Volantis-minos/public/words public >nul 2>nulecho Merge/move finished ...call hexo deploypause--><h3 id="结语"><a href="#结语" class="headerlink" title="结语"></a><strong>结语</strong></h3><p>貌似又是一大波折腾，但都比较简单，重点是如果可以获得一个比较舒适的写作空间，那这也是值得的。</p></body></html>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;html&gt;&lt;head&gt;&lt;/head&gt;&lt;body&gt;&lt;p&gt;很久没有静下心来写东西了，总是沉迷于搞些小玩意儿，比如小插件、小工具，主站的主题越来越复杂强大，这也算是我一天天看着成长起来的，然而我却掉队了，依然徘徊在2.0版本，没什么理由，只是觉得自己喜欢修修补补，今天搞个特效，明天加个功能，很有趣我也很入迷。但最近越来越觉得，我正在远离创作者的阵营，离“开发者”又相距甚远，所以为了纠正下状态，我唯一能做且想做的，就是找回书写的乐趣，更进一步讲，是找回不断总结的习惯。为此，我翻了一堆主题，力图寻找到一个专注写作专注文字的主题，很幸运，icarus的主题作者的另一主题minos，完美的迎合了我的口味，简洁但绝非简单，扩展比较全面。因此就有这个页面啦。今后的日子里，我会在这里放英语文章、中文随想或者是非技术类的文字向文章，欢迎多多支持！&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="站点" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/categories/%E7%AB%99%E7%82%B9/"/>
    
    
    <category term="介绍" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/%E4%BB%8B%E7%BB%8D/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Important rules in English writing</title>
    <link href="https://www.cz5h.com/words/9aa4.html"/>
    <id>https://www.cz5h.com/words/9aa4.html</id>
    <published>2021-01-31T23:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-02-07T15:25:52.900Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<html><head></head><body><p>Most young scientists have no clue how to organise their writing, let alone how to get it done. And when they finally do write a sentence, they immediately rewrite it. This struggle continues for months until they end up with a piece of writing that does not make them happy. For many scientists, the adventure of creating new knowledge starts and ends in the nightmare. And that is not a surprise. You did not choose to become a scientist because you liked writing so much. But writing is the endpoint of your research, and it all begins with reading.</p><a id="more"></a><h3 id="Sentences"><a href="#Sentences" class="headerlink" title="Sentences"></a><strong>Sentences</strong></h3><p><strong>Sentences are great because they,</strong></p><ul><li>produce images in our mind (a)</li><li>have natural rhythm (n)</li><li>make us curious (a/i)</li><li>are short and varied in length (n)</li><li>affect our emotion (i)</li><li>are clear (n)</li><li>are intriguing (a/i)</li><li>spark your imagination (a)</li><li>seem to lead somewhere (i)</li><li>use simple everyday words (n)</li><li>are easy to read (n)</li><li>are active (n/a)</li></ul><p><code>Love to have a smoke</code>. ordinary<br><code>Love to have a smoke</code>, he sighed prose<br><code>Love is smoke, made with the fume of sighs</code> poetry</p><p>From smoking to Shakespeare in two simple steps, with exaggeration as the means to get there. This is all very nice, but how to apply this to your own writing and develop your skills at the sentence level? </p><ul><li>The first step is to make sure to write natural sentences.  To achieve that, you need to know which aspects of your writing tend to become unnatural.</li><li>The second step is to make your sentences more activating by improving the texture of your writing. </li></ul><p>This can be done by subtly exaggerating the nature of your sentences. If your sentence is questioning, it works to make it even more questioning. If the main quality is clarity, it is better to make it even clearer.</p><p><strong>They are clear and direct because they,</strong></p><ul><li>convey the message as simple as possible</li><li>present one idea or one comparison</li><li>avoid excessive use of subclauses</li><li>avoid excessive length</li><li>only provide necessary information</li><li>potentially enhance the structure*</li></ul><p><strong>They are natural, so they,</strong></p><ul><li>have commas to help the reader breathe</li><li>have natural rhythm<ul><li>with regular beats</li><li>avoiding obnoxious beginnings</li><li>avoiding excessive ending</li><li>avoiding irregular staccato beats</li><li>avoiding mid-sentence endings</li></ul></li><li>use simpler words if possible</li><li>use an active voice rather than a passive voice</li><li>have a clear message</li><li>have their verb and subject not too far apart</li></ul><p><strong>They exaggerate the natural qualities so they,</strong></p><ul><li>essentially read like somebody is talking to you</li><li>continuously draw the attention of the reader*</li><li>make you see the picture behind the words*</li><li>are easy to read out loud</li></ul><h3 id="Sentence-pitfall-exercises"><a href="#Sentence-pitfall-exercises" class="headerlink" title="Sentence pitfall exercises"></a><strong>Sentence pitfall exercises</strong></h3><h4 id="1-Aiming-to-write-as-simple-as-possible"><a href="#1-Aiming-to-write-as-simple-as-possible" class="headerlink" title="1. Aiming to write as simple as possible"></a><strong>1. Aiming to write as simple as possible</strong></h4><blockquote><p><strong>[Original]</strong>. The evolution of a spatially structured population composed of genetically different species is given by the frequency of a specific species in space and time, that is the fraction of the number of individuals of that species over the total number of individuals.</p></blockquote><p><strong>[Better]</strong>. A spatially structured population composed of genetically different species evolves over space and time. This evolution we can quantify by the frequency of a specific species. This quantity is the fraction of the number of individuals of that species over the total number of individuals.</p><h4 id="2-Presenting-one-idea-or-comparison"><a href="#2-Presenting-one-idea-or-comparison" class="headerlink" title="2.Presenting one idea or comparison"></a><strong>2.Presenting one idea or comparison</strong></h4><blockquote><p><strong>[Original]</strong>. From a preventive perspective, it is crucial to identify proactively which persons or population segments run a high risk, and under what conditions, to go through the full pathological trajectory, or to identify such a risk in those who are already suffering.</p></blockquote><p><strong>[Better]</strong>. It is crucial to identify persons, patients or segments of the population who run a high risk for going through the full pathologic trajectory. From a preventive perspective, we need to do this in a pro-active way.</p><h4 id="3-Avoiding-subclauses-amp-brackets"><a href="#3-Avoiding-subclauses-amp-brackets" class="headerlink" title="3.Avoiding subclauses &amp; brackets"></a><strong>3.Avoiding subclauses &amp; brackets</strong></h4><p>The end of the subclause should then allow the reader to have a natural pause before the original sentence continues with movement again. This example shows how it’s done:</p><p>This sentence comes to a halt, and that provides the space for a subclause, (pause) after which we can easily get back to the original sentence.</p><p>Remember two things:</p><ul><li>You will never be able to write everything down, so you need to be selective anyway.</li><li>The fact that what you write is true does not mean it should be included. Only write what you really need in order to tell the story.</li></ul><h4 id="4-Avoiding-excessive-length"><a href="#4-Avoiding-excessive-length" class="headerlink" title="4.Avoiding excessive length"></a><strong>4.Avoiding excessive length</strong></h4><p>some rules of thumb:</p><ol><li>A sentence is the expression of a single idea.</li><li>You really need a good reason to make a sentence longer than a line and a half.</li><li>If you can’t read it out loud in a single breath, it is probably too long.</li></ol><h4 id="5-Only-giving-necessary-information"><a href="#5-Only-giving-necessary-information" class="headerlink" title="5.Only giving necessary information"></a><strong>5.Only giving necessary information</strong></h4><blockquote><p><strong>[Original]</strong>. Studying the dynamics and fluctuations of pesticide concentrations in lettuce and more specifically the leaves of the lettuce plant that was grown under increased light and UV radiation we found that…</p></blockquote><p><strong>[Better]</strong>. Studying the dynamics of pesticide concentrations in lettuce leaves, grown under increased light and UV radiation we found that…</p><h4 id="6-Possibly-enhancing-the-structure"><a href="#6-Possibly-enhancing-the-structure" class="headerlink" title="6.Possibly enhancing the structure"></a><strong>6.Possibly enhancing the structure</strong></h4><blockquote><p><strong>[Original]</strong>. You can measure the density using an optical probe or a density sensor.</p></blockquote><p><strong>[Better]</strong>. You can measure the density using either an optical probe or a density sensor.</p><figure class="highlight plain hljs"><table><tbody><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br><span class="line">2</span><br><span class="line">3</span><br><span class="line">4</span><br><span class="line">5</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">either ... or</span><br><span class="line">neither ... nor</span><br><span class="line">not only ... but also</span><br><span class="line">both ... and</span><br><span class="line">whether ... or</span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure><h4 id="7-Using-commas-to-help-the-reader-breath"><a href="#7-Using-commas-to-help-the-reader-breath" class="headerlink" title="7.Using commas to help the reader breath"></a><strong>7.Using commas to help the reader breath</strong></h4><p>Common uses of commas:</p><ol><li>Near the start of the sentence, often after an adverb or adverbial phrase (“However, it is still the best option” “By the way, let me know when you’re finished”)</li><li>To ‘subordinate’, to indicate part of a sentence that is not grammatically necessary, but adds to the meaning, often making a comment on it. (“Everyone turned up, which was great, and was very happy, which was even better”)</li><li>To separate two halves of a sentence (“If you want to go, I will stay here”)</li></ol><h4 id="8-Using-natural-rhythm"><a href="#8-Using-natural-rhythm" class="headerlink" title="8.Using natural rhythm"></a><strong>8.Using natural rhythm</strong></h4><p><strong>8.1 Obnoxious beginnings &amp; excessive endings</strong></p><blockquote><p><strong>[Original]</strong>. L-arabinose and D-xylose are the most abundant monosaccharides in nature after D-glucose, being major constituents of the hemicelluloses xylan and xyloglucan, and of pectin.</p></blockquote><p><strong>[Better]</strong>. The most abundant monosaccharides in nature after D-glucose are L-arabinose and D- xylose. They are the major consti-tuents of the hemicel-luloses xylan and xylo-glucan, and of xylan and xyloglucan, and of pectin.</p><blockquote><p><strong>[Original]</strong>. Xylitol is the first common intermediate of the inter-connected L-arabinose and D-xylose fungal catabo-lism.</p></blockquote><p><strong>[Better]</strong>. The chemical compound Xylitol is the first common intermediate of the inter-comnected L- arabinose and D-xylose fungal catabolism.</p><p><strong>8.2 Staccato Writing</strong></p><p>In spoken language emphasis is used in a regular way. In writing, this regularity can be disturbed, which leads to unnatural rhythm and difficult reading. The steps to tackle this problem are:</p><ul><li>Find the points where you trip over the text by reading it out loud.<br>Circle the parts that carry substantial emphasis and look for local concentrations of emphases.</li><li>Play with the order of words or add words that tend to speed up to make it more smooth.</li></ul><p><strong>8.3 Tail in the middle of the dog</strong></p><p>It best avoided as it causes the latter part of the sentence to come across like an unimportant side remark. The solution is either to remove the last part, or turn it into a new sentence.</p><blockquote><p><strong>[Original]</strong>. Carbonyl sulphide is the most abundant sulphur containing trace gas in the atmosphere, with an average mixing of 500 parts per trillion.</p></blockquote><p><strong>[Better]</strong>. Carbonyl sulphide is the most abundant sulphur containing trace gas in the atmosphere. It has an average mixing of 500 parts per trillion.</p><h4 id="9-Use-simpler-words-if-possible"><a href="#9-Use-simpler-words-if-possible" class="headerlink" title="9.Use simpler words if possible"></a><strong>9.Use simpler words if possible</strong></h4><p>find the lofty words and change them for simpler ones. Sometimes it helps to think of an image, example or metaphor for something to make clear what you are talking about.</p><h4 id="10-Using-active-voice-rather-than-passive"><a href="#10-Using-active-voice-rather-than-passive" class="headerlink" title="10.Using active voice rather than passive"></a><strong>10.Using active voice rather than passive</strong></h4><ul><li><p><strong>Passive</strong><br>The data were provided by the detector.<br>The electron density has been increasing over time.<br>The medicine was given to the patient every other day</p></li><li><p><strong>Active</strong><br>The detector provided the data<br>The electron density increased over time<br>The patient got the medicine every other day</p></li></ul><h4 id="11-Provides-a-clear-message"><a href="#11-Provides-a-clear-message" class="headerlink" title="11.Provides a clear message"></a><strong>11.Provides a clear message</strong></h4><h4 id="12-Having-the-verb-and-subject-not-too-far-apart"><a href="#12-Having-the-verb-and-subject-not-too-far-apart" class="headerlink" title="12.Having the verb and subject not too far apart"></a><strong>12.Having the verb and subject not too far apart</strong></h4><h4 id="13-Essentially-reads-like-somebody-talks-to-you"><a href="#13-Essentially-reads-like-somebody-talks-to-you" class="headerlink" title="13.Essentially reads like somebody talks to you"></a><strong>13.Essentially reads like somebody talks to you</strong></h4><h4 id="14-Draw-the-reader’s-attention-continuously"><a href="#14-Draw-the-reader’s-attention-continuously" class="headerlink" title="14. Draw the reader’s attention continuously"></a><strong>14. Draw the reader’s attention continuously</strong></h4><h4 id="15-Make-you-see-the-picture-behind-the-words"><a href="#15-Make-you-see-the-picture-behind-the-words" class="headerlink" title="15. Make you see the picture behind the words"></a><strong>15. Make you see the picture behind the words</strong></h4><h4 id="16-Are-easy-to-read-out-loud"><a href="#16-Are-easy-to-read-out-loud" class="headerlink" title="16. Are easy to read out loud"></a><strong>16. Are easy to read out loud</strong></h4><h3 id="Conflict-induces-in-stories"><a href="#Conflict-induces-in-stories" class="headerlink" title="Conflict induces in stories."></a><strong>Conflict induces in stories.</strong></h3><p><strong>Phase 1: The exposition</strong></p><p>In the Mr. Bean story the exposition starts at the beginning and goes to the point where he is eager to give a coin. (0:00-0:19 m:s)</p><p><strong>Phase 2: Propelling moment</strong></p><p>The propelling moment in Mr. Bean is less dramatic, but very effective. He wants to give a coin, but he only has a banknote! (0:19-0:22 m:s)</p><p><strong>Phase 3: Divergent Action Phase</strong></p><p>In the Mr. Bean clip the divergent action phase is of course much shorter. It consists of: being annoyed for not having a coin, trying to walk away, trying to find some change and finally getting stuck, because he has no options left. (0:22- 0:41 m:s)</p><p>Divergence cannot go on for ever of course. If we keep stacking on problems, the story would never end. To reach a solution we need something that changes divergence into convergence. Some kind of key to solve the problem.</p><p><strong>Phase 4: Crucial Event</strong></p><p>In Mr. Bean he gets an idea ‘maybe I can earn a coin myself’. In Romeo and Juliet it is the moment that Romeo does not get the letter.</p><p><strong>Phase 5: Convergent Action Phase</strong></p><p>Mr. Bean gets the next idea when he finds his handkerchief, performs his unforgettable dance, and is given a coin by a woman passing by (0:42-1:08 m:s). If you’ve watched the movie and I’d stop there, you’d feel the tension. You want the conflict to be resolved and your desire fulfilled. You know it is just about to happen. But if I do not give it, you will feel the tension because you just love to surrender yourself to a story.</p><p><strong>Phase 6: Solution</strong></p><p>This is the moment the conflict is resolved. The Mr. Bean story does have a happy end and he solves the conflict by giving his coin at 1:08 m:s.</p><p><strong>Phase 7: Coda</strong></p><p>As we had to deal with a lot of action, trouble and conflict we want to stabilise the situation. To give us time to let go of the tension, we are presented with a bit of nothing. Perhaps some comic relief or a futile conflict from the start that gets solved, leading to a glorious ‘That’s all<br>folks’. The Mr. Bean story does have a happy end and he solves the conflict by giving his coin at 1:08 m:s.</p><h4 id="Applying-stories-in-your-papers"><a href="#Applying-stories-in-your-papers" class="headerlink" title="Applying stories in your papers"></a><strong>Applying stories in your papers</strong></h4><ul><li><p><strong>Exposition</strong><br>You can of course the beginning of your introduction.</p></li><li><p><strong>Obstacle</strong><br>In most cases you have an obstacle, otherwise you did not have to do all the work.</p></li><li><p><strong>Divergent Action Phase</strong><br>This feels a bit more tricky because we discovered it is about stacking problems, where the situation becomes more complicated and finally gets stuck. With your paper you need to realise that your divergent phase started in your introduction already. There is a default divergent quality in the part where you share what you are going to do, and which question and sub-questions you aim to answer, i.e. where you share an overview of your paper. The only challenge lies in writing the method section as it’s fairly dry. But there are enough divergent action options in your results and discussion section.</p></li><li><p><strong>Crucial Event</strong><br>The only story feature you really need to turn the second half of your paper into a story is a crucial event. If you have a key insight, or an idea that leads you to solve the conflict, use it here.</p></li><li><p><strong>Convergent Action Phase</strong><br>Whatever comes after that, can serve as a convergent phase. If you secretly add speed by increasing the event density in this part of your results and discussion section, you can suggest the speed of a converging part while everybody reads a ‘normal’results and discussion section.</p></li><li><p><strong>Solution</strong><br>And finally you present your solution or conclusion to solve the conflict in your paper. Easy, as you do that in a paper anyway.</p></li><li><p><strong>Coda</strong><br>A look at possible future work is excellent material to build a coda with.</p></li></ul><h3 id="Writing-Process"><a href="#Writing-Process" class="headerlink" title="Writing Process"></a><strong>Writing Process</strong></h3><ol><li>What is a <strong>sketch</strong>? A sketch can consist of a drawing or a table of contents for that specific section. Whatever it is, you need to have a clear idea what to write before you start the actual writing.</li><li>If you have that idea, you can do a <strong>warming up</strong> to clear the pathway from your mind to the page. The easiest warm up is to write about any subject like your neighbours’ dog or the weather.</li><li>Please write for a set time, and make sure you do not stop writing. When the flow of words stops, you repeat writing the last word again and again until new words start to flow again. That allows you to open up the path from your thoughts to the page.<br>Once you’ve made a sketch and done your warm up, you write your text without correcting it. In the scheme it says ‘<strong>write crap</strong>’. </li><li>To be clear, don’t write any crappier than you normally would. The point is to only focus on producing text and to accept anything that is not perfect. Imperfections are for the <strong>editing phase</strong>.</li></ol><h4 id="The-five-phases-in-the-writing-process"><a href="#The-five-phases-in-the-writing-process" class="headerlink" title="The five phases in the writing process"></a><strong>The five phases in the writing process</strong></h4><p>In the end there is not one generic plan that is the best for everybody, just as writing is not a linear process. You go back and forth many times and that is good, because you do not know what you will write until you write it down. And with every polishing step you become wiser. Whatever the steps are in reality, you will always find that you iterate between the following five phases:</p><ul><li><strong>The write before you do anything phase</strong><br>In which you make plans for your research. Writing will help you to make these plans concrete, tangible and clear enough to execute.</li><li><strong>The research phase</strong><br>In which you do your research and collect material to write about. It is possible to go back to the first phase to change your plans if necessary.</li><li><strong>The sketching phase</strong><br>In which you sketch your article in detail.</li><li><strong>The writing phase</strong><br>In which you do the actual writing.</li><li><strong>The editing phase</strong><br>In which you edit what you wrote.</li></ul><h3 id="Ongoing…"><a href="#Ongoing…" class="headerlink" title="Ongoing…"></a><strong>Ongoing…</strong></h3></body></html>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;html&gt;&lt;head&gt;&lt;/head&gt;&lt;body&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most young scientists have no clue how to organise their writing, let alone how to get it done. And when they finally do write a sentence, they immediately rewrite it. This struggle continues for months until they end up with a piece of writing that does not make them happy. For many scientists, the adventure of creating new knowledge starts and ends in the nightmare. And that is not a surprise. You did not choose to become a scientist because you liked writing so much. But writing is the endpoint of your research, and it all begins with reading.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="English" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/categories/English/"/>
    
    
    <category term="writing" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/writing/"/>
    
    <category term="notes" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/notes/"/>
    
    <category term="training" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/training/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Try to explain the projections.</title>
    <link href="https://www.cz5h.com/words/32f0.html"/>
    <id>https://www.cz5h.com/words/32f0.html</id>
    <published>2021-01-24T23:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-02-07T15:25:52.900Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<html><head></head><body><p>Multi-dimensional data is a very important type of data since it covers almost every kind of dataset. Most of them could be formatted into regular tables or datasheets, where the columns are called their dimensionalities. Researchers already have a lot of experience dealing with these datasets, but in the age of big data, the expansion of the number of dimensionalities (columns) is already made it big trouble for people to handle them.</p><a id="more"></a><p>Researchers have created a huge amount of methods to reduce the dimensionality to let people could find insight information in an understandable way. The basic idea is to compute the importance of different dimensions and preserve the principle dimensionalities (PCA). If dimensionality reduced to 2 or 3, then we can understand them, because it’s easy to show them reduce data with 2D or 3D space. But the problem is the losing details could play a big role in the process of our understanding. How to find these missing messages or how to evaluate the result of dimensionality reduction has become a key problem. In other words, giving good explanations to these results is the final aim that we want to reach.</p><p>With extra interactions, some methods could let people have global explanations by adding axes to the 2/3D space. But they can’t give much more local explanations,  meanwhile, the existing methods that have local explanations are all heavily dependent on interactions.<br>Thus, we introduced the image-based method to compute the local explanations. It allows users to get local explanations and could complete the computation in one time without extra interaction. We designed three models to compute the local information and finally created six methods to test. We used more than 20 datasets to test every method and gave detailed illustrations to these explanations we get. Using the intrinsic structure we have known, we verified the rationality of our explanations. </p><p>Now, this research is still moving on, the future work will focus on the fluence of different parameters, and the evaluation methods for our explanations. With multiple good explanations we computed, we aim to give users more extra understanding so that guide them to choose the best dimensionality reduction method to handle their dataset.</p></body></html>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;html&gt;&lt;head&gt;&lt;/head&gt;&lt;body&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multi-dimensional data is a very important type of data since it covers almost every kind of dataset. Most of them could be formatted into regular tables or datasheets, where the columns are called their dimensionalities. Researchers already have a lot of experience dealing with these datasets, but in the age of big data, the expansion of the number of dimensionalities (columns) is already made it big trouble for people to handle them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="English" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/categories/English/"/>
    
    
    <category term="writing" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/writing/"/>
    
    <category term="introduction" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/introduction/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Some writing pitfalls</title>
    <link href="https://www.cz5h.com/words/e86a.html"/>
    <id>https://www.cz5h.com/words/e86a.html</id>
    <published>2021-01-20T23:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-02-07T15:25:52.900Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<html><head></head><body><p>Pitfalls are some dangerous areas that most people could stuck in when they write their words. Keep them in mind could be a good way to avoid meeting them, and also you can use these pitfalls to test or valid your exsiting words/sentences to see if you are in or out of them.</p><a id="more"></a><h4 id="Absence-of-emphasis"><a href="#Absence-of-emphasis" class="headerlink" title="Absence of emphasis"></a><strong>Absence of emphasis</strong></h4><p>If your sentence carries no emphasis the message reads like a futile message. Try to change the order of the messages or words in the sentence so emphasis gets back in.</p><h4 id="Articles"><a href="#Articles" class="headerlink" title="Articles"></a><strong>Articles</strong></h4><p>Notably writers from Asia forget to use articles which are not present in their own language. Please mark articles in a newspaper text and become more aware of them in your own writing</p><h4 id="Brackets"><a href="#Brackets" class="headerlink" title="Brackets"></a><strong>Brackets</strong></h4><p>Information between brackets is best avoided, unless it is a definition of an abbreviation.</p><h4 id="Commas"><a href="#Commas" class="headerlink" title="Commas"></a><strong>Commas</strong></h4><p>Commas are ideally placed where you reader should breathe. If this is in your list of pitfalls you do not use them enough, or too often or at the wrong place.</p><h4 id="EE-end"><a href="#EE-end" class="headerlink" title="EE/end"></a><strong>EE/end</strong></h4><p>Excessive Endings:  If you use double emphasis at the end of a sentence, the movement of the text disappears. If it is completely gone when the text should move on, it is an excessive ending [ee]. If the loss of movement is less severe we tend to add [end] in the text. The question is then if you wanted it to end or not. We doubt that it is the case.</p><h4 id="Grammar"><a href="#Grammar" class="headerlink" title="Grammar"></a><strong>Grammar</strong></h4><p>If this is added in your text we wonder whether the sentence is grammatically correct. In that case expert help on grammar is a good idea, or you can use Grammarly to help you out.</p><h4 id="Long"><a href="#Long" class="headerlink" title="Long"></a><strong>Long</strong></h4><p>Long Sentences. Sentences longer than 24 words are difficult to read. Try to make a chain of shorter sentences and play with sentence length for sake of variation.</p><h4 id="MM"><a href="#MM" class="headerlink" title="MM"></a><strong>MM</strong></h4><p>Many Messages: We can read one or two messages per sentence. If you have many messages in your sentence you overwhelm the reader. Try to make a chain of simple sentences instead of one complicated sentence. </p><h4 id="OB-strong-beginning"><a href="#OB-strong-beginning" class="headerlink" title="[OB]/strong beginning"></a><strong>[OB]/strong beginning</strong></h4><p>Obnoxious Beginnings: Sentences that begin with big emphasis do not read naturally. In that case you use an obnoxious beginning [OB]. Playing with the order of the messages in the sentence can solve the problem. If the effect is less pronounced we speak of [strong beginning]. In that case it is not a big problem, but it is something to be aware of.</p><h4 id="Plural-Singular"><a href="#Plural-Singular" class="headerlink" title="Plural/Singular"></a><strong>Plural/Singular</strong></h4><p>In English ‘one thing makes’ and ‘two things make’. This is sometimes written in the other way around.</p><h4 id="Simpler-structure"><a href="#Simpler-structure" class="headerlink" title="Simpler structure"></a><strong>Simpler structure</strong></h4><p>Simpler sentence structure: If your sentences are too complex, the complexity obstructs the communication. Try to make a chain of simple sentences instead of one complicated sentence.</p><h4 id="Simpler-words"><a href="#Simpler-words" class="headerlink" title="Simpler words"></a><strong>Simpler words</strong></h4><p>If you use simpler words the message reaches the mind of the reader more easily.[Simpler]</p><h4 id="More-direct"><a href="#More-direct" class="headerlink" title="More direct"></a><strong>More direct</strong></h4><p>This is a combination of simpler structure and simpler words.</p><h4 id="stacc"><a href="#stacc" class="headerlink" title="stacc"></a><strong>stacc</strong></h4><p>Staccato: Irregular beats in a sentence are called staccato</p><h4 id="Sub"><a href="#Sub" class="headerlink" title="Sub"></a><strong>Sub</strong></h4><p>Subclauses: Subclauses distract the reader. Please give the information a separate sentence or leave it out. You can also reshuffle the information within the sentence so the subclause disappears.</p><h4 id="Subclause-like-structure"><a href="#Subclause-like-structure" class="headerlink" title="Subclause like structure"></a><strong>Subclause like structure</strong></h4><p>The same as subclauses but then more subtly shaped in the sentence.</p><h4 id="Tail"><a href="#Tail" class="headerlink" title="Tail"></a><strong>Tail</strong></h4><p>Tail in the middle of the dog: This is double emphasis in the middle of a sentence</p><h4 id="Variation-in-sentence-length"><a href="#Variation-in-sentence-length" class="headerlink" title="Variation in sentence length"></a><strong>Variation in sentence length</strong></h4><p>Your text needs more variation in sentence length to prevent the reader from losing attention over sentence length monotony. Please also use very short sentences!</p><h4 id="Variation-in-sentence-structure"><a href="#Variation-in-sentence-structure" class="headerlink" title="Variation in sentence structure"></a><strong>Variation in sentence structure</strong></h4><p>If this is in your pitfall list, your sentence use the same build up. Become aware of that form and try to vary more.</p><h4 id="Xmas-diner-paragraphs"><a href="#Xmas-diner-paragraphs" class="headerlink" title="Xmas diner paragraphs"></a><strong>Xmas diner paragraphs</strong></h4><p>If you have a paragraph that covers half a page or more you write Xmas diner paragraphs. For psychological reasons it is best to use lines of white make the reading hurdles doable.</p></body></html>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;html&gt;&lt;head&gt;&lt;/head&gt;&lt;body&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pitfalls are some dangerous areas that most people could stuck in when they write their words. Keep them in mind could be a good way to avoid meeting them, and also you can use these pitfalls to test or valid your exsiting words/sentences to see if you are in or out of them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="English" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/categories/English/"/>
    
    
    <category term="pitfalls" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/pitfalls/"/>
    
    <category term="writing" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/writing/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>2020年终总结(A)随便写写</title>
    <link href="https://www.cz5h.com/words/28d8.html"/>
    <id>https://www.cz5h.com/words/28d8.html</id>
    <published>2020-12-30T23:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-02-13T03:19:47.342Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<html><head></head><body><p>2020年最后一天终于到了，没有什么期待浑浑噩噩的一年到此就结束了，搁心自问获得了什么？好像除了年长一岁，再无其它值得细说的事情，疫情的肆虐完全打乱了正常的学习节奏，还有那种远离家乡的孤独，无法言说。</p><a id="more"></a><p>我是个没太有”良心的人，出门在外便可以于父母于不顾，这种”冷血”或许也是支撑我走到如此地步的原因，不知道这条道路是不是正确的，但不争的事实是，一年光景已逝，空留嗟叹。是想出关之前，也曾假想过生活的美好，但却未曾料到这天灾人祸。当初，这不过是一场不起眼的感冒，谁曾想事情会发展到如此地步。2020年，新冠疫情，无疑是导致今天这一局面的最魁祸首。</p><h3 id="章节一：西方价值体系的全面崩塌"><a href="#章节一：西方价值体系的全面崩塌" class="headerlink" title="章节一：西方价值体系的全面崩塌"></a><strong>章节一：西方价值体系的全面崩塌</strong></h3><p>从年初开始，伴随着中国疫情的不断恶化，以美国为首的西方阵营不断在大洋对岸进行抹黑和唱衰，用”隔岸观火”来形容再合适不过了，但哪曾想，”人共命运共同体”这个概念，会这么快的得到体现，全球的相继沦陷让我们大跌眼镜，在惊诧为什么西方国家如此不甚的同时，西方世界却未曾一刻停止他们的丑恶言论。时值特朗普大选时期，他更是使用所谓的”中国肺炎”来歪曲这次疫情，群情激愤下，中外舆论场展开了一场关于东西方体制的大讨论。</p><p>记得几个月前导师也曾问过我为什么中国的防疫做的这么好，这不是一个表象问题，其内在深层次的原因在于制度在于文化，西方的文艺复兴过分强调个体价值和体验，同时期欧洲的小国体制又无法培养一个大国利益集团，从而导致人们普遍的过度关注自身利益，”无恒产者有恒心”，这或许是对中国近代无产阶级兴起的一个有效解释，相比于西方的价值观无疑更具有凝聚力。</p><p>另外，我还延伸到了更深层次的儒家文化。中国的传统文化影响同样不能忽视，小到”听妈妈的话”，大到”忠君爱国”，可以说，儒家思想以及忠孝观念自古就被统治者用来约束臣子和人民，所以 中国人的内心普遍存在一把”道德的尺子，这个尺子讲的是于家庭内”顺父母”（孝顺）于朝堂上”顺君王”（忠君），除此之外，才是法律的约束。于此点而言，西方的社会道德，由于家庭结构的破碎，即子女和父母的松散关系，导致人们从小便以”顺自己”为基本价值观，进而影响整个社会管理治理体制的制定，议会制的产生，正是由于”集权寡头”形式无法被人民认可，从下至上，相互影响，这是我以为的西方社会形成的一种解释。</p><p>于此早在秦汉时期，东方的中国就开始探索了，事实上，可以说秦朝的灭亡就源于法家思想的弊病，过份依赖严苛的秦法，使民怨声载道，侧面验证机械的执行法条是行不通的，且法律制定者由上层控制，导致法律并不总是以人为本，所以西方民主社会有了立法机构，这一定程度上解决了这一问题，但也让他们过度的追求了”法律的作用”而忽视了文化。所以当西方政府去要求人们居家隔离时，政府反而会成为人民心中破坏自己利益的凶手，当没有文化层面的”妥协”时，那这种”限制”就会转变为”无法认同的不合理”，进而暴发各种抗议行为。你可以说这是公民意识的崛起，这个概念也曾在国内被炒的火热，但今年看来，这种一味追求各体利益的”意识”简直可笑至极，随着基层群众普遍的”认清现实”，以美国为首的西方世界从上世纪末开始的对中国的和平演变可以休矣。</p><p>谈完了思想层面，再谈谈制度层面。</p><p>当今的西方，无论是美国等大国还是欧洲等小国，均没有成熟的中央政府。例如美国，自建国开始的联邦政府就不对各州政府有绝对的控制。虽有美联储，但依然无法统筹各州政府的运行。这种尴尬的局面，造成了今年的纽约州同联邦政府决裂的现象 。另外，美国的另一问题是，近乎完善的医疗体系均面向富人阶层，诸如呼吸机等稀缺设备均在高级诊所或医院，也就是说平民正常是去不了也去不起的，这在和平稳定的时期不会暴露问题，但当面对疫情时，大量的底层民众需要医疗资源，这时，美国传统的医疗体制就彻底失效了。又因为联邦政府的权力有限，所以无法统筹调度全国资源导致各州政府各自为战， 进而导致拥有”全球最多医疗资源”的国家在如此疫情面前的不堪一击。对于欧洲，情况又变的稍有不同，小政府主义胜行， 导致面对疫情时政府的责任意识不强，过度的遵循公民决议，又导致政策的反复无常和防疫措㢮的严重滞后。在正常状态下，小政府可以给公民比较好的体验，试想你会被邀请针对某具体政策来投票以决定该政策是否执行，这是小国的优势。但也是一切弊病的来源，一体两面有良就有弊，该种体制下，公民被赋予过度的权力，当灾难来临，小政府无法有效组织全体国民，同时由于资本主义国家的运作机制导致资源并不完全掌握在政府手中，在协调资源时，资源生产方和政府的利益并不一定趋同，例如本地厂家会刻意保持口罩的稀缺性，这有利于维持早期的高定价，但无疑对疫情有害，要知道中国可以花50块 买200片口罩，但在荷兰，50片口罩售价就可到80元钱。</p><p>值得一提的是大国在制度上也是有”纵深”的，这种防疫纵深，可以允许全国省份支援武汉的现象出现，但这需要两个要求，一是强有力的中央政府，二是群众的奉献意识，目前纵观西方世界，无论大国还是小国，都缺少制度优势，群众也缺乏互助意识，所以，除去前期”轻敌”导致的疫情蔓延，亦或是说重视后采取的措施，各个西方国家均不合格，防疫的亮点均在亚州，这和深层次的文化基础是密切相关的。</p><p>总之，2020年的新冠，让自由女神之像彻底崩塌，伴随着美国对中国贸易战的完全失败和特朗普的选举失利，中美博弈已经进入中国时间，2021年的”疫苗大战”，相信在分配上西方世界会暴露更多的问题出来。我为什么会如此关注呢，因为在这次的”东风压过西风”的过程中，我很不幸的处在西风里，虽然无奈，但也收获不少，一年的时间，看尽西方国家的各种招数，”帝国主义亡我之心不死”这话现在也适用，对我来说，这一年真就是”眼看他起高楼，眼看他宴宾客，眼看他楼塌了”。有人说在海外时间长了容易被洗脑，但这在我看来完全是错误的理解，公知的误导对国人的杀伤力才是最大的，关于”外国的月亮圆不圆”，我的看法是”一看便知”，切莫相信那水中月，只能让你们竹篮打水一场空。</p><p>吐嘈完疫情，好像就没有什么好写的了，这场疫情真的是浪费了太多的时间，到现在为止，我的学校依然没有恢复正常运行， 所谓的”居家办公”和”视频会议”并不能解决长时间居家带来的社交缺乏，所以上半年自己独租时，看电视剧成了消磨时间的方法，仔细想想，或许<br>这还真是个值得拿出来说说的话题。</p><h3 id="章节二：在影视剧中沦陷"><a href="#章节二：在影视剧中沦陷" class="headerlink" title="章节二：在影视剧中沦陷"></a><strong>章节二：在影视剧中沦陷</strong></h3><p>细细想来，《大明风华》是来这里看的第一部局，是2019年的压轴历史剧，像极了今年《大秦赋》的状态。后来，找电影时无意间发现了《上车走吧》，这下让我喜欢上了管虎的作品风格，从此开始，我便看了《外乡人》和《生存之民工》，对现实的刻画太真实深刻了，现在已无人能达到当年的编导水平了。后来把一部苦苦寻找多年未果的老电视剧给看了，那就是中国历史上第一部防疫题材的电视剧《黑菌》，时值疫情肆虐，这个电视剧真就把”封村”、”言论管制”、”官员不作为”等等现象刻画的淋沥尽致，作为一部同时具有些惊悚感的电视剧我看完后感觉意犹未尽，遂找到了另一部甚称前无古人后无来者的恐怖电视剧：《魂断楼兰》，可以说是极尽恐怖气氛，当然也写出了人性的黑暗和无奈。本质是部以惊悚包装的犯罪片。之后一段时间，又看了管虎的一些作品，比如《黑洞》和《冬至》，陈道明的演技，无论是黑恶势力，还是底层银行职员，都演的太棒了，尤其是《冬至》，极尽压抑和绝望，看完真的是让人致郁。而《黑洞》我认为是国产犯罪剧的巅峰了，没有非黑即白，更多的观感，是一种陷入黑暗的绝望。</p><p>看过的电视剧，整理下的话，可以按题材分类。</p><ul><li>历史剧：《康熙王朝》《雍正王朝》《大明风华》《大秦赋》《楚汉传奇》</li><li>反腐剧：《国家使命》《使命》《黑洞》《国家形象》《沉默》《高纬度战栗》大部分是张嘉益作品。</li><li>现实题材：《黑菌》《不要和默生人说话》《魂断楼兰》《外乡人》《生存之民工》</li></ul><p>看电视剧不仅是消遣，更多的是寻找一种心灵寄托，比如《外乡人》中的包工头，无奈辛酸但却有一邦值得托付的邻里，《民工》中的农民群体，在中国腾飞的大浪潮里，挣扎着维护自己那最后一点尊严。又像是《高伟度战栗》中的劳爷，坚守着那个对党的忠诚和对正义的初心。这些都是使人向善的一发人深思的优秀剧集，可惜随着我们的国家越来越强大，软实力不断的增强，但真正探讨内部问题的剧集却越来越少，现代言情剧，时代追思剧成为日下的主流，欣欣向荣的景象往往会掩盖许多阴暗处的问题，而这些老剧，无疑是很好的反醒催化剂，细细想来，假如现在有人像《冬至》里男主那样私吞钱财，那他会有男主那般内心的挣扎吗，恐怕难矣。</p><h3 id="终章"><a href="#终章" class="headerlink" title="终章"></a><strong>终章</strong></h3><p>现在是31号晚上的十一点半，晚上刚刚和房东家吃过火㶽，算是疫情期间难得的一次聚会了。外面现在是一轮明月当空，稀稀落落的鞭炮声在耳边响着，仔细听远处的广场上还有人在外放音乐，我也想立刻出门加入他们，但现实的状况告诉我不能去，这既是居于他人屋檐下的无奈，也是疫情期间对自己的负责，所以，有时候真得很纠结，既想摆脱他们过属于自己的生活，但疫情却是现实中无情的洪水猛兽每当我有此想法时就立刻在我脑海中出现吓退我。总之，此地好像成了我无法跳跃出去的”舒适区”。</p><p>窗外的鞭炮声更密集了，我想，定是无数的家庭在庆祝属于他们的春节。于我而言，上个元旦上个春节，这个元旦及这个春节都将在遥远的海外独自度过，这或许是房东家能给到我的一丝温暖了，但睹物思人，看他们合家团圆的景象，又何尝不是种残酷。</p><p>马上就是这里的12点整，也意味着我正式的步入2021，过去的一年无论如何也都随风而逝，能留下的也就只有些记忆碎片了，如果要用几个关键词定义，那我觉得应该是”无奈”、”失望”、”迷茫”、”焦虑”和”孤独”，对疫情的无奈，对政策的失望，对自己未来的迷茫，对现状的焦虑，以及那深深根植于自己内心的孤独。或许这些无奈这些孤独是我人生的财富，但这些实在是并非我所愿，2021年，希望尽快摆脱疫情影响（虽然我知道并不现实），过一个真正属于我的、快乐的、充满斗志和希望的一年。2021我准备好了，来吧。</p></body></html>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;html&gt;&lt;head&gt;&lt;/head&gt;&lt;body&gt;&lt;p&gt;2020年最后一天终于到了，没有什么期待浑浑噩噩的一年到此就结束了，搁心自问获得了什么？好像除了年长一岁，再无其它值得细说的事情，疫情的肆虐完全打乱了正常的学习节奏，还有那种远离家乡的孤独，无法言说。&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="Daily_Life" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/categories/Daily-Life/"/>
    
    
    <category term="瞎写" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/%E7%9E%8E%E5%86%99/"/>
    
    <category term="生活" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/%E7%94%9F%E6%B4%BB/"/>
    
    <category term="总结" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/%E6%80%BB%E7%BB%93/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Understand complex tables in one minute</title>
    <link href="https://www.cz5h.com/words/8267.html"/>
    <id>https://www.cz5h.com/words/8267.html</id>
    <published>2020-12-02T23:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-02-07T15:25:52.900Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<html><head></head><body><p>Here you have a normal data table in your hand. It could include thousands of rows and columns, and usually, the items are all numerical numbers, which are hard to understand. Now, your task is to get information from it as much as possible.  </p><a id="more"></a><p>What can you do with the data? How could you find useful information from it?</p><h3 id="Exposition"><a href="#Exposition" class="headerlink" title="Exposition"></a><strong>Exposition</strong></h3><p>The general way is to compute some statistical features. But if you want to get a good comprehension of it, you need to find more meaningful features, like clustering information of rows and relationships between different columns.</p><p>To do this, you can use some advanced methods like principal components analysis which is known as PCA. But the numerical result of these methods is still hard to understand. So, here we introduce visual signals while using these methods.</p><p>For example, with PCA, you can get a squeezed result, which means the number of rows won’t change but columns could be compressed into 2 or 3. Since columns indicate dimensional information,  you can say the dataset is transformed from high-dimension to low-dimension,  which you can easily visualize as a scatterplot in the coordinate system. </p><p>Now, you can get the scatterplot in which every row represents a point, and they could gather into different clusters. We naturally think these clusters are the clustering features of this dataset. And if you assign different colors into different clusters, then you can understand it immediately.</p><h3 id="Propelling-Moment"><a href="#Propelling-Moment" class="headerlink" title="Propelling Moment"></a><strong>Propelling Moment</strong></h3><p>But the question is that since PCA is just one of so many algorithms, how could you make sure the PCA could give you a proper result. Can you trust it? The short answer is No. We need a way to test it.  </p><h3 id="Divergent-Action-Phase"><a href="#Divergent-Action-Phase" class="headerlink" title="Divergent Action Phase"></a><strong>Divergent Action Phase</strong></h3><p>Here we compute two kinds of neighbor errors by testing every point in the scatterplot.</p><p>What are the neighbors? If points are located in a circle area around the one we selected, then we call them their neighbors.<br>We use the classic Euclidean distance to find out all neighbors of each point in the low-dimension scatterplot and the original high-dimension data. </p><p>Next, we can compare these two kinds of neighbors. For the point of low-dim scatterplots, if its neighbors don’t appear in high-dim data, then we call them false-neighbors. And if the points of low-dim scatterplots miss some neighbors of high-dim data, then we call these missing-neighbors. </p><h3 id="Crucial-Event"><a href="#Crucial-Event" class="headerlink" title="Crucial Event"></a><strong>Crucial Event</strong></h3><p>Now, we get important errors! that could tell you which part of the scatterplot we can trust and which part is totally wrong. </p><h3 id="Convergent-Action-Phase"><a href="#Convergent-Action-Phase" class="headerlink" title="Convergent Action Phase"></a><strong>Convergent Action Phase</strong></h3><p>The next question is how to assign these error messages to our scatterplot? </p><p>There are several ways to do it. We can use luminance to represent errors with the original scatterplot or we just generate a new scatterplot with colors to show errors.<br>With the above methods, we could have several visual results of the original dataset.</p><h3 id="Solution"><a href="#Solution" class="headerlink" title="Solution"></a><strong>Solution</strong></h3><p>So now, you have 3 views. Using the scatterplot of PCA, you 1can easily understand the clustering information. And with these error views, we can easily correct the former understanding. Actually, this kind of solution could be used as a general process, we can also compute other types of views to refine our understanding. </p><h3 id="Coda"><a href="#Coda" class="headerlink" title="Coda"></a><strong>Coda</strong></h3><p>So, you can see these visual methods able you to have a good comprehension of the table in a short time. That’s why we call it: understand complex tables in one minute!</p></body></html>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;html&gt;&lt;head&gt;&lt;/head&gt;&lt;body&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here you have a normal data table in your hand. It could include thousands of rows and columns, and usually, the items are all numerical numbers, which are hard to understand. Now, your task is to get information from it as much as possible.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="English" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/categories/English/"/>
    
    
    <category term="presentation" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/presentation/"/>
    
    <category term="slides" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/slides/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>我眼中的《姜子牙》——三界官场现形记</title>
    <link href="https://www.cz5h.com/words/9e2f.html"/>
    <id>https://www.cz5h.com/words/9e2f.html</id>
    <published>2020-11-16T23:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-02-07T19:55:24.626Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<html><head></head><body><p><strong>十年前，时值汉东省人事更替</strong></p><p>副省长人选尊某因破获“11.11”特大走私案件，一举打掉了本省最大的走私集团实力，并且揪出了该势力和其竞争对手-时任组织部部长魏九的密切联系，致使魏九被离职审查，后经领导班子决议，尊某成功上任汉东省副省长，由此，汉东省步入了杜绝走私的经济发展快车道。</p><a id="more"></a><p>魏九落马，被限制在其老家清水市进一步审查，一年之后，汉东省全省筹备召开“杜绝走私研讨会暨暂1111大案表彰大会”，尊副省长亲自致电时任清水市公安局长姜涯，要求其尽快将魏九依法定罪逮捕。</p><p>姜局长终于见到了最终BOSS。一年前的“猎狐行动”他还记忆犹新，部分顽固份子拼死抵抗，致使行动过程出现一死两伤，后经查证清水市作为龙头重镇经济受到了走私势力的严重侵蚀，此刻于公于私，姜涯都想赶紧给魏九定罪，一切都在稳步推进，但就在向检察院递交材料的前夜，魏九在家中和姜涯见了一面，这“违规”的见面，竟透露给了姜局长一个秘密…</p><p>当年的走私大案，另有隐情。密会中，魏九给了一个人的资料给姜局长，她叫九妹，在1111大案中以被抓获羁押候审，卷宗显示其涉嫌多起走私和挪用公款案件，和魏九有密切联系，过了今晚的材料递交，应该会定重罪入狱，但魏九却说，她是清白的。</p><p><strong>九妹是无辜的？案子不能结！</strong></p><p>姜局长力排众议，终究没能在当晚递交材料，而同一晚，魏九动用了所有关系，给九妹制造了无罪证据。当晚姜局和尊副省长告知了他的想法，或者说信念：一个人的清白都不顾，何以顾一方平安？尊副省长听罢大怒，他让姜涯冷静几天好好反思自己的立场，并让其他人暂时接替他的工作。</p><p>几天后，魏九还是锒铛入狱，姜局长被停职反省，其得力干将们也遭受到了非议和排挤，出乎意料的是，九妹因证据不足被免于起诉，不日就被释放，自此猎狐行动正式结束，姜局原本作为清水市公安局长应该被嘉奖提拔，但现在却落得个无官一身轻。</p><p>那时候，姜局每天都泡在离家不远的酒馆里，不料那一天，竟然碰到了那个女人：九妹。</p><p>作为城郊的酒馆，本该非常普通，但一年前公安部执行猎狐行动时，前线指挥部就在这里，准确的说是把这当场了临时食堂，自然有些信息会在这里被流出，老板耳濡目染，对整个“1111答案”的大小事也可以算是门儿清。九妹来这的目的，就是为了调查她父亲的事情。她一直以为他父亲兢兢业业，不理解为何会触犯法律，于是她想以一己之力查明真相。</p><p>姜涯见状，顺水推舟，承诺和他一起调查，查明真相或许也是对当年自己的一个交代。</p><p><strong>在后来的接触中，姜涯逐渐了解了九妹的身世…</strong></p><p>九妹的父亲是轴网科技集团的高管，轴网科技是当时清水市名噪一时的大企业，九妹大学毕业后就被安排进了公司给总裁做秘书，其父用意不言自明，后来她和总裁轴某，也确实发展为了男女朋友，不过与此同时，当时已经身为南高县县长的魏九，也把魔抓伸向了她。</p><p>当时年少青春的九妹，只把魏九当做忘年交，亦师亦友，在后来轴网科技的发展中，作为轴某的女友，在魏九的蛊惑下给轴网的发展提了很多非法“建议”，在魏九的暗中运作下，轴网集团一发不可收拾，凭借着非法获利，其在当时迅速建立了一个庞大的、以高新科技为外衣的走私帝国，霸占了当时的各大财经版面。九妹就这样，被魏九当做“影子”操控了轴网集团，而作为“领导有方”的魏九也从此发迹，人脉势力迅速扩张。以至于十年前，已经担任省委组织部长，成了接任副省长的热门人选。</p><p><strong>帝国的崩塌非一朝一夕。</strong></p><p>轴网集团的辉煌，只持续了两年，之后，由于轴某的资金管理不善、人事经营散乱，整个集团资金链出现严重问题，魏九早已升任组织部长，时任县长只得为其“输血”试图挽救，但随着各种集团黑幕的爆出，对轴网集团讨伐的社会舆论已经充斥了整个南高县、清水市，在不断涌现出来的大量的事实证据面前，汉东省委终于带头开展了猎狐行动。</p><p>行动波及面之广，几乎涉及了清水市的各行各业，那段时间一众上市公司停牌整顿，不少民营企业也因资金管理问题被迫吞下天价罚单，行动虽是为了打击走私违法势力，但其对整个清水市造成的负面效果，姜涯是深有体会的。而九妹，就在这大起大落中，饱受了生活的摧残，而她自始至终都不知道，她一直如棋子般任人摆布，终究不得安宁的生活。</p><p>了解到这里，姜涯终于大概明白了为何魏九说九妹是无辜的，了解到了猎狐行动对清水市尤其是南高县的负面影响。他依旧不解的问题是：从南高县一路升上去的魏九，在猎狐行动如此高调的前提下自然难逃干系，或者说，猎狐行动，就是针对魏九的一次行动？</p><p>在整理了九妹的全部资料后，姜涯悉数递交给了纪委监委，姜不知道的是，这一举动，直接导致1111案件的主要犯罪嫌疑人魏九因为犯罪证据不实而被重审，这可谓是“放虎归山”！尊副省长获悉此事，立刻给当时负责工作的清水市领导施压，并动用自己的关系，暗地里将魏九给九妹伪造的证据“不合法”的毁掉，因此，在姜涯上报材料几天后，九妹就重新因为涉嫌违法被羁押。</p><p>姜涯隐约觉得，有人故意要把九妹和魏九“捆绑”在一起置于死地。几天后姜涯得知九妹的证据被认为改动，勃然大怒，咆哮着要揪出内鬼，在市公安局大闹一番之后，他获得了这样一个他不愿接受的消息：是尊副省长下的命令。</p><p><strong>为什么，尊副省长如此急切的想要封口魏九，还有九妹？</strong></p><p>带着这个问题的疑惑，仍在停止反省的姜局长亲自到省委拜会尊副省长，当面质问此事，而尊副省长只是语重心长的说了一句：这是我做的有利于整个清水市的最好安排！谈话间，尊副省长还特别提到了九妹的状况，并对姜涯说：如果你真希望还她正常生活，就让她彻底和魏九断了联系，把她送到美国的贵婿大学读书去吧，他可以给九妹写介绍信。</p><p>从省委回来，姜涯越发不解和愤懑，但他仍然是想还九妹清白和正常生活的，所以，按尊副省长的意思，九妹顺利出狱，并且安排准备出国，在临行前的一天，九妹特地来和姜涯道谢。</p><p>姜涯说：到了美国你就可以有新的生活了。<br>九妹说：警察不会骗人吧？！</p><p>这段时间的相处，让姜涯感觉九妹就像自己的女儿，送她出国或许今生再无机会见面，不舍之满满，但最终，九妹还是如约离开了姜涯进入了贵婿大学。</p><p>这边温情的送走了九妹，那边“放虎归山”的魏九并没有闲着，虽然尊副省长在他被重审后的第二天就立刻吩咐了自己的亲信督办这个案子，但魏九脱离了监狱，还是如鱼得水，所有关系网立刻重启，一场魏九的“绝地反击”就要来了。</p><p><strong>他撕掉了贵婿大学的遮羞布！</strong></p><p>魏九在宝贵的时间里，发动了一切关系，曝光了位于美国的贵婿大学，原来这所大学是赤裸裸的权钱交易的产物，经调查，该校就读中国学生有半数是清水市内有名企业家的子女，他们被安排在那里读书且不被允许回国！到此，舆论为之哗然，同样，姜涯也大吃一惊，因为他知道，让他送九妹过去的尊副省长，一定和这有脱不了的干系。</p><p>与此同时，尊副省长也不顾组织纪律，越级行使权力，给清水市公安局直接施压，让他们以最快速度了解魏九的案子。另一边，得知贵婿大学的内幕后，姜涯内心做了激烈斗争，难道他一直听命于一个不忠于国家不忠于人民的领导？为了证实这个可怕的想法，他总结了近期收集的全部资料，无奈的发现所有的证据都指向尊副省长，在此情形下，姜涯没有忘记自己是一名警察、是一名人民公仆，既然领导队伍中有问题，那就该改正，无奈自己身份，他只得将所有材料交给了媒体。</p><p><strong>自此，猎狐行动的始末以及尊副省长和魏九之间的关系终于大白于天下。</strong></p><p>时间回到十年前，由汉东省委政法委牵头，省公安厅、纪委监委等部门组成联合调查组，对清水市轴网集团以及市县级领导班子展开全面调查。公安内部行动代号“猎狐”，时值领导班子换届，尊某和魏九作为牵头小组成员，心里都知道行动成败对自己的意义。</p><p>同时尊某对魏九的所作所为都知道的非常清楚，虽然尊某也有些问题，但都没触及原则，所以在这方面尊某算是牢牢地抓住了魏某的把柄。猎狐行动开始之前，两人就曾多次私人碰面，后经调查，当时尊某就对魏九以前程为要挟，让其促成猎狐行动的成功，从而让他成功接任副省长之职。魏九无奈，只能答应，他可以“出卖”他的走私利益链，但他要求魏某接任后保留他的权力。</p><p><strong>猎狐行动开始前夜，魔鬼契约签订了。</strong></p><p>但后来事态的发展，是魏九始料未及的，原来尊某一早就在利用魏九，尊某打算让魏九彻底在官场出局，一是为了干掉主要竞争对手，二是为了掩盖这个“和魔鬼签订的契约”。因此，在猎狐行动后期，尊某已接任省长，但他丝毫没有停止的意思，最后居然把魏九的所有势力赶尽杀绝，这也是为什么魏九非要置尊副省长于死地的原因。</p><p>这一切经媒体报道，引发了社会的广泛热议，而姜涯被舆论推上了风口浪尖，不只是因为他的客观公正，更是因为他敢于挑战权力！省市领导班子出现严重分歧和非议，这是上级领导所不愿看到的事，纪委监委介入调查，确认了尊某当年不当竞争的事实，但在任无其他问题且工作作风扎实，暂不对其进行人事调整，而姜涯因为违反组织纪律，被调任其他部门接受进一步的工作安排。</p><hr><p><strong>地点：</strong><br>汉东省 from 电视剧《人民的名义》<br>清水市 from 电视剧《使命》<br>南高县 from 电视剧《阳光代表》 </p><p><strong>人物：</strong><br>尊副省长 - 小九<br>魏九 - 苏妲己（九尾）<br>九妹 - 小九<br>姜涯 - 姜子牙</p><p><strong>角色行动名称自行代入，文笔有限，不严谨处请见谅。</strong></p></body></html>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;html&gt;&lt;head&gt;&lt;/head&gt;&lt;body&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;十年前，时值汉东省人事更替&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;副省长人选尊某因破获“11.11”特大走私案件，一举打掉了本省最大的走私集团实力，并且揪出了该势力和其竞争对手-时任组织部部长魏九的密切联系，致使魏九被离职审查，后经领导班子决议，尊某成功上任汉东省副省长，由此，汉东省步入了杜绝走私的经济发展快车道。&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="Daily_Life" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/categories/Daily-Life/"/>
    
    
    <category term="影评" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/%E5%BD%B1%E8%AF%84/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>东北亚离战争到底有多远？</title>
    <link href="https://www.cz5h.com/words/abcd.html"/>
    <id>https://www.cz5h.com/words/abcd.html</id>
    <published>2020-08-17T22:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-02-07T16:40:40.445Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<html><head></head><body><p>这是一部经典的“韩国式”政治剧情片，不过值得称赞和肯定的，是其又继续往前迈了一步，大胆的描绘了东北亚的一次隐晦的热战危机，虽然剧情“浮夸”经不起推敲，但当世界局势真的变得波云诡谲之时，谁又能保证世界不是朝着远离和平的方向前进？</p><a id="more"></a><div style="position: relative; width: 100%; height: 0; padding-bottom: 75%;">    <iframe src="//player.bilibili.com/player.html?aid=968959116&amp;bvid=BV1Up4y1i7Be&amp;cid=213305756&amp;page=1" scrolling="no" border="0" frameborder="no" framespacing="0" allowfullscreen="true" style="position: absolute; width: 100%; height: 100%; left: 0; top: 0;"></iframe></div><h4 id="1-整体观感"><a href="#1-整体观感" class="headerlink" title="1. 整体观感"></a><strong>1. 整体观感</strong></h4><p>战争迷表示吃到饱，将近一大半的篇幅都花在“热战”情节，其中又有一大半集中在朝鲜的核潜艇内，不同势力、不同思想聚集在这小小的潜艇内，在外部超强台风“钢胚”的映衬下，显得格外的渺小，但就是这渺小的一叶小舟，孱弱的维系着美、朝、韩三方的和平对峙，中间又夹杂着中、日两大外部势力的干预，真可谓是战争的“风暴眼”。</p><p>全篇的主旨，个人觉得就是片尾韩国总统对人民的发问：你们想统一吗？这句话的深刻含义是，朝韩的半岛统一，决定因素不是中美日外部因素，而是朝韩两国人民。</p><p>此主题隐晦的另一面，表现在对“中朝同盟”的否定，这个意图，在电影中表现的很明显，反叛的总督长不止一次的强调“同中国的血盟”，即便临死仍然坚信这一点，为此不惜在计划曝光后仍然（按中方意图）向日本发射核弹，当然“勇敢的”韩国总统跳出来阻止了这一切，他的行为同时也间接影响了美朝领导人的想法，并最终促成了最后的 happy ending.</p><h4 id="2-半岛的排他性"><a href="#2-半岛的排他性" class="headerlink" title="2. 半岛的排他性"></a><strong>2. 半岛的排他性</strong></h4><p>在无数次说完佩服韩国电影的脑洞之后，这里必须得再说一次。当然，如果你看多了韩国的战争片，即便是朝韩内战，他们也拍了一大堆精彩的宣扬“朝韩一家亲”的电影。所以把朝鲜领导人“美化”到一定高度，并且和韩国领导人思维在同一层次，这是一种“现实无法达到”的剧情，即便如此，韩国电影依旧热衷于这样做，目的我觉得有二：一是在韩国内部进行“内宣”，维持韩国人的统一情节；二是对全世界说“朝韩不是敌人、是朋友”，这在当下正和文在寅的一些执政思路相吻合。由此种“朝韩一家亲”的情怀推延出来的，是一种“半岛排他性”，其核心就是：</p><p>朝鲜半岛的事情由朝鲜半岛自己解决。</p><p>这当然是个美好的梦，不仅对面的朝鲜办不到（中国不答应），就连韩国自己也办不到（韩美共同防御条约）。最现实的是：《韩美共同防御条约》存在一天，韩国就不配说这句话，当然在电影情节中是可以说的，不过，在《铁雨2》中，我们可以发现导演故意弱化了美国驻韩司令部的作用，电影里是美国副总统直接远程指挥，到最后是韩国总理给军队下令，这在现实是不可想象的。可以参照一些别的电影剧情比如《白头山》里美驻韩司令部的强势，战时基本可以凌驾在韩国国防部之上。</p><h4 id="3-东北亚离战争到底有多远"><a href="#3-东北亚离战争到底有多远" class="headerlink" title="3. 东北亚离战争到底有多远"></a><strong>3. 东北亚离战争到底有多远</strong></h4><p>东北亚包括中日朝韩俄美（驻军）六方势力，这也是所谓“朝核六方会谈”的成员，各个国家内部都有所谓的“鹰派/极右翼”分子，当六方权力均掌握在温和派手中，那自然是地区稳定，但只要一方内部权力斗争，极右翼掌握权力，在各方的制衡拉扯中就会失去平衡，从而导致不可预知的危险举措，进而影响区域和平。这样看来，东北亚局势的核心，目前就在朝鲜半岛，而朝鲜半岛局势的核心，就在失衡的朝鲜一侧，前段时间朝鲜单方面炸毁开城工业园的朝韩联络办公室，就是个危险举动，朝鲜内部的真实斗争我们不得而知，但如果你关注朝鲜的政治，通过支离破碎的报道，也能发现金正恩上台之后对下层官员的清洗，和对权力组织结构的改革，所谓的“先军政治”正在在金正恩的领导下朝“党国体制”过渡，姑且算作是朝鲜的一种改革开放，金正恩掌权下正在力图弱化军队对国家治理的干预，重新将劳动党回归到应有的党的地位，这是一种不走老路的“创新”，势必会有内斗，时至今日，金正恩已经连续多个月没有公开露面，对于他的健康状态的猜测一度成为新闻焦点。</p><p>在如此现实下，你还能笑着说，朝鲜很稳定吗？现实是：朝鲜动，则韩国动，韩国动，则美国动，美国动，则中俄动，则日本动，这是种不可停止的“链式反应”，为什么要六方会谈促成“半岛无核化”，就是为了将此反应链的不确定性降到最低，然而事实呢，任重而道远。</p><p>影片中，朝美签署和平协议是在2021年7月左右，目前来看，几无可能，当下中美对抗直接硬碰硬，朝鲜在这种情况下已经失去“平衡作用”，美国目前可见的招数基本都打在台湾，或许美国更希望用“台湾牌”这张更“直接”的杀手锏来制衡中国，在这种情况下，朝鲜半岛无核化、以及朝韩和平的日程都要被延后，这就是现实的无情和残酷。</p><h4 id="4-朝鲜无核后何去何从"><a href="#4-朝鲜无核后何去何从" class="headerlink" title="4. 朝鲜无核后何去何从"></a><strong>4. 朝鲜无核后何去何从</strong></h4><p>这也是《铁雨2》中朝鲜内部产生矛盾的根本问题，放弃核武，朝鲜能换来什么？片中给出的答案实在过于“理想化”，韩国有部分人认为，最好的状态就是达成一种“南北帮扶”，即回归到“朝鲜半岛的事情朝鲜半岛自己解决”，他们认为韩国有能力帮助朝鲜过渡到正常国家，事实如此，但这种情况并不会出现，原因就是中美日俄的影响。</p><p>半岛和平稳定自然是好事一桩，但对于周边大国，朝鲜半岛已然成为一个“准”代理人战争场地，朝鲜之于中俄，更多的是一种和“美帝同盟”的“缓冲带”，很不幸，作为一个国家，就是这样无奈，也正是如此，不甘于做“护城河”的朝鲜走了一招险棋，即发展核武，当然这不是一蹴而就，也不能说这违背或顺从了中国的意愿，各方的权力都在变化，不同时代做出的决策也不尽相同，不论如何，历史走到今天，朝鲜已经不单单是“缓冲带”这么简单了，其有了更多的“独立国格”，虽然依旧站在中俄一遍，但却需要更多的束缚，一旦把控不好，其引起的地区动荡会比以往更加严重。</p><p>说到朝鲜的核武发展，离不开其假想敌美国的存在，如果美国领导权更替，势必对朝政策会有改变，这对于韩国来说也是一样，政权更迭导致半岛局势变化，这是个不争的事实。目前的状态是：亲北的文在寅+虽然狠但不寻常的川普+有革新思想的金正恩，这是一个历史的契机，共同作用下促成了“金川会”等等一系列“高难度”政治操作，然鹅即便如此，朝鲜也只是做了些许退让，并没有做出什么实质性的操作。可以预见的是，当下没做到的事情，在下一个美国总统任期，也基本是下一个韩国总统任期内，依然很难做到。（目前看川普和文再演都很难连任）</p><h4 id="5-反思"><a href="#5-反思" class="headerlink" title="5. 反思"></a><strong>5. 反思</strong></h4><p>我完全赞同将这种“意淫”剧情划为政治宣传的范畴，虽然Low了一点，但只少能让看的人明白一些事情，剧情再怎么YY，只要你看到最后，如果你是个韩国人，那句“你想统一吗”肯定会直击你的内心，这可以算得上是一种高级内宣了吧，对此我们需要多加学习！</p><p>政治剧情片算是韩国电影的一大特色了，而更进一步包含战争因素的也有很多了，以往都是着重在朝韩内战，到后来的“朝韩间谍”情节，再到“反美情节”，例如《战疫》，再到将“中美日”因素全部糅杂在一起，以朝鲜半岛为中心，创造出区域热战甚至是世界大战的剧情，这部《铁雨2三方会谈》不是第一次（《白头山》也是中美朝韩），当然也不会是最后一次，韩国已经成功探索出一条以现实为基础，演绎夸大为手段的政治剧情电影的路线，可以预见类似电影（中美频频出镜）以后会越来越多。</p><p>在这方面，我们的表现呢？战争片九成都是抗战或内战题材，发人深思即有内涵的并不多，到了偏剧情的战争片，更是缺乏剧情张力。我觉得诸如《战狼2》《红海行动》等就是不错的探索，虽然更加偏重战争，但总归是包含一些剧情的。港片的《赤道》等也是一种方向，不过其可能需要更加宽松的审核环境。感叹一声，不再赘述。</p><h4 id="后记"><a href="#后记" class="headerlink" title="后记"></a><strong>后记</strong></h4><p>总而言之，这部的三方会谈，铺垫够足、剧情张力够大、结局够完美，作为一部标准的“韩式”YY剧情片，包含有足够量的政治、战争、人文情节，剧情紧凑不拖拉，如果你忘掉《铁雨1》，抛弃现实情节来观影，这绝对可以算一部上乘佳作。</p></body></html>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;html&gt;&lt;head&gt;&lt;/head&gt;&lt;body&gt;&lt;p&gt;这是一部经典的“韩国式”政治剧情片，不过值得称赞和肯定的，是其又继续往前迈了一步，大胆的描绘了东北亚的一次隐晦的热战危机，虽然剧情“浮夸”经不起推敲，但当世界局势真的变得波云诡谲之时，谁又能保证世界不是朝着远离和平的方向前进？&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="Daily_Life" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/categories/Daily-Life/"/>
    
    
    <category term="影评" scheme="https://www.cz5h.com/words/tags/%E5%BD%B1%E8%AF%84/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
